Hello.
مرحبا.
I'm a toy developer.
أنا مطور ألعاب.
With a dream of creating new toys that have never been seen before,
عندي حلم أن أصنع ألعابًا لم تر من قبل،
I began working at a toy company nine years ago.
بدأت أعمل في شركة ألعاب منذ تسع سنوات.
When I first started working there,
عندما بدأت العمل هناك،
I proposed many new ideas to my boss every day.
كنت أقترح لمديري أفكارًا جديدةً كل يوم.
However, my boss always asked
و مع ذلك، كان يسأل دومًا
if I had the data to prove it would sell,
إن كانت لدي البيانات لإثبات أن اقتراحاتي سوف تباع،
and asked me to think of product development after analyzing market data.
وطلب مني أن أفكر في تطوير المنتجات بعد تحليل بيانات السوق.
Data, data, data.
بيانات، بيانات، بيانات
So I analyzed the market data before thinking of a product.
لذا حللت بيانات السوق قبل التفكير بالمنتج.
However, I was unable to think of anything new at that moment.
مع ذلك، لم اكن قادرًا على التفكير بأي شيء جديد في هذه اللحظة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My ideas were unoriginal.
أفكاري لم تكن مبتكرة.
I wasn't getting any new ideas and I grew tired of thinking.
لم أكن قادرًا على جلب أي أفكارٍ جديدةٍ وتعبت من التفكير.
It was so hard that I became this skinny.
لقد كان الأمر صعبًا جدًا لدرجة أني أصبحت بهذا النحف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's true. (Applause)
إنها حقيقة. (تصفيق)
You've all probably had similar experiences and felt this way too.
على الأغلب جميعكم مررتم بتجارب مماثلة و شعرتم بهذا أيضًا.
Your boss was being difficult. The data was difficult.
مديري كان صعبًا والمعطيات كانت صعبة.
You become sick of thinking.
فتمرض من التفكير.
Now, I throw out the data.
الآن، تخلّصت من المعطيات.
It's my dream to create new toys.
حلمي أن أصنع ألعابًا جديدة.
And now, instead of data,
والآن، عوضًا عن البيانات،
I'm using a game called Shiritori to come up with new ideas.
أستخدم لعبة اسمها (شيريتوري) لخلق أفكارٍ جديدة.
I would like to introduce this method today.
أود اليوم ان أقدم هذا الأُسلوب.
What is Shiritori?
ما هو شريتوري؟
Take apple, elephant and trumpet, for example.
على سبيل المثال، خذ تفاحة، فيل، وبوق.
It's a game where you take turns saying words
إنها لعبة حيث تأخذ فيها دورك لتقول كلمات
that start with the last letter of the previous word.
تبدأ بآخر حرف من الكلمة السابقة.
It's the same in Japanese and English.
إنها نفس اللعبة باليابانية والإنجليزية.
You can play Shiritori as you like:
يمكنك أن تلعب شيريتوري كيفما تريد.
"neko, kora, raibu, burashi," etc, etc. [Cat, cola, concert, brush]
"neko, kora, raibu, burashi," إلخ،إلخ. [قط، كولا، حفلة، فرشاة]
Many random words will come out.
ستظهرا لكثير من الكلمات العشوائية.
You force those words to connect to what you want to think of and form ideas.
ستجبر هذه الكلمات على الإتصال بما تريد التفكير به و تشكّل الأفكار.
In my case, for example, since I want to think of toys,
في حالتي، على سبيل المثال، منذ ان أردت التفكير في الألعاب،
what could a toy cat be?
ماذا يمكن أن تكون عليه لعبة قط؟
A cat that lands after doing a somersault from a high place?
قطة تهبط بعد تدحرجها من مكان عالٍ؟
How about a toy with cola?
ماذا عن لعبة كولا (المشروب الغازي)؟
A toy gun where you shoot cola and get someone soaking wet?
مسدس لعبة يطلق كولا لتبليل أحدهم؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ridiculous ideas are okay. The key is to keep them flowing.
لا بأس بالأفكار السخيفة. و السر هو إبقائها متدفقة.
The more ideas you produce, you're sure to come up with some good ones, too.
كلما أنتجت المزيد من الأفكار، تكون متأكدًا أنه بإمكانك الإتيان بأفكار جيدة أيضًا،
A brush, for example. Can we make a toothbrush into a toy?
فرشاةٌ ما، كمثال. هل يمكننا تحويل فرشاة الأسنان إلى لعبة؟
We could combine a toothbrush with a guitar and --
بإمكاننا دمج فرشاة الأسنان مع غيتار -- و...
(Music noises) --
(ضجيج موسيقى)
you've got a toy you can play with while brushing your teeth.
ستحصل على لعبة تلعب بها بينما تنظف أسنانك.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Kids who don't like to brush their teeth might begin to like it.
الأولاد الذين لا يحبون تنظيف أسنانهم قد يبدأون بتنظيفها.
Can we make a hat into a toy?
هل يمكننا أن نحول قبعة إلى لعبة؟
How about something like a roulette game, where you try the hat on one by one,
ماذا عن لعبة كاللعبة الدوارة حيث يجب تدوير القبعة من واحد لآخر،
and then, when someone puts it on, a scary alien breaks through the top
و من ثم، عندما يضعها أحدهم، يبرز منها مخلوقُ فضائي مخيف في الأعلى
screaming, "Ahh!"
يصرخ, "آآآآآآه!"
I wonder if there would be a demand for this at parties?
أتساءل ما إذا كان سيكون عليها طلب في الحفلات؟
Ideas that didn't come out while you stare at the data will start to come out.
الأفكار التي لم تظهر عندما كنت تحدّق في البيانات تبدأ بالظهور.
Actually, this bubble wrap, which is used to pack fragile objects,
في الحقيقة، كيس الفقاقيع الذي يستخدم في لف الأشياء القابلة للكسر،
combined with a toy, made Mugen Pop Pop,
مدمجًا بلعبة، صار لعبة (ماغن بوب بوب)،
a toy where you can pop the bubbles as much as you like.
و هي لعبة تستطيع أن تفقع بها الفقاقيع على قدر ما تريد.
It was a big hit when it reached stores.
لقد كانت لعبة مطلوبةً جدًا عندما وصلت الأسواق.
Data had nothing to do with its success.
البيانات لا علاقة لها بنجاحها.
Although it's only popping bubbles,
بالرغم من أنها عبارة عن فقاقيع تفقع،
it's a great way to kill time,
إنها طريقة ممتازة لقتل الوقت،
so please pass this around
لو سمحت مرروها
amongst yourselves today and play with it.
بينكم و العبوا بها اليوم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Anyway, you continue to come up with useless ideas.
على كل، ستستمر بإيجاد أفكارٍ لا نفع لها.
Think up many trivial ideas, everyone.
فكروا بالعديد من الأفكار التافهة، جميعكم.
If you base your ideas on data analysis and know what you're aiming for,
فلو بنيتم أفكاركم على تحليلات البيانات و تعرفون ما هو هدفكم،
you'll end up trying too hard,
ستنتهون بمحاولات صعبة جدًا،
and you can't produce new ideas.
و لن تستطيعوا إنتاج أفكارٍ جديدة.
Even if you know what your aim is,
حتى ولو كنتم تعرفون ما تهدفون إليه،
think of ideas as freely as if you were throwing darts with your eyes closed.
فكروا بأكبر قدرٍ من الحرية في أفكاركم و ارموا السهام بأعينٍ مغلقة.
If you do this, you surely will hit somewhere near the center.
لو فعلتم هذا، فبالتأكيد ستصيبون مكانًا قريبًا من الوسط.
At least one will.
واحدًا منها على الأقل سيصيب.
That's the one you should choose.
هذا هو السهم الذي عليك اختياره.
If you do so, that idea will be in demand
لو فعلتم هذا، ستبقى هذه الفكرة مطلوبة
and, moreover, it will be brand new.
و علاوةً على ذلك، ستكون علامةً تجاريةً جديدة.
That is how I think of new ideas.
هكذا أفكر بأفكارٍ جديدة.
It doesn't have to be Shiritori; there are many different methods.
لايجب أن تكون (شيريتوري)، هناك العديد من الأساليب مختلفة.
You just have to choose words at random.
عليك فقط بالتفكير بكلمات لا على التعيين.
You can flip through a dictionary and choose words at random.
تستطيع أن تقلّب بالمعجم وتختار كلمات عشوائية.
For example, you could look up two random letters and gather the results
على سبيل المثال، تستطيع البحث في حرفين و من ثم جمع النتائج
or go to the store and connect product names
أو الذهاب إلى المتجر و تصل أسماء المنتجات
with what you want to think of.
بما تريد التفكير به.
The point is to gather random words,
الهدف هو جمع حرفين عشوائيا،
not information from the category you're thinking for.
و ليس معلومات من الفئة التي تفكر فيها.
If you do this, the ingredients for the association of ideas are collected
إن فعلت هذا، فإن مكونات الأفكار المترابطة ستجمع
and form connections that will produce many ideas.
و تشكل روابط ينتج عنها العديد من الأفكار.
The greatest advantage to this method is the continuous flow of images.
الأفضلية العظمى التي يملكها هذا الأُسلوب هي الاستمرارية بتدفق الصور.
Because you're thinking of one word after another,
لأنك ستكون تفكر في كلمةٍ تلو اﻷخرى،
the image of the previous word is still with you.
و صورة الكلمة السابقة ستبقى معك.
That image will automatically be related with future words.
و هذه الصورة ستتصل تلقائيًا بكلماتٍ مستقبلية.
Unconsciously, a concert will be connected to a brush
بلا وعي، ستتصل حفلة موسيقية بفرشاة
and a roulette game will be connected to a hat.
و اللعبة الدوارة ستتصل بقبعة.
You wouldn't even realize it.
لم تكن حتى مدركًا لها.
You can come up with ideas that you wouldn't have thought of otherwise.
ستأتي بأفكارٍ لم تكن قد فكرت بها في جميع اﻷحوال.
This method is, of course, not just for toys.
طبعا، هذا الأسلوب ليس فقط للألعاب.
You can collect ideas for books, apps, events, and many other projects.
تستطيع جمع أفكار لكتب، تطبيقات، أحداث، و العديد من المشاريع اﻷخرى.
I hope you all try this method.
آمل أن تطبقوا جميعكم هذا الأسلوب.
There are futures that are born from data.
هناك مستقبل يولد من البيانات.
However, using this silly game called Shiritori,
مع ذلك، باستخدام هذه اللعبة السخيفة التي تدعى شيريتوري،
I look forward to the exciting future you will create,
أتطلع إلى المستقبل المثير الذي ستصنعونه،
a future you couldn't even imagine.
مستقبل لم تكونوا قد فكرتم به من قبل.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)